Prologue

The young man and the old master stood on opposite sides of the bridge. It wasn't a very long bridge, maybe thirty or forty yards across. It was made of wood and curved gently over the stream below. The stream was only knee height at its deepest, so the bridge was as much for ornament as it was for function. But it was the only proper entrance to the grounds of the old monastery.

The young man stood on the outside looking in. He remembered these grounds. He had been an apprentice here not all that long ago. He was no longer welcome.

The young man spoke first. "Do you know why I am here?"

"I do."

The young man chose to stand another moment in silence. It was night, and the crescent moon was high in the sky. He enjoyed the cool breeze against his face and hair.

Then his posture shifted slightly and his staff tapped gently on the wood below his feet. The master shifted at the same moment. The duel had begun.

The young man focused. He was master of a secret power. If he calmed his mind, he could perceive the future. Not perfectly, of course. The future could never be perceived perfectly. It was always changing, shifting. But he could see the future as a web of possibility, infinite in complexity. Some paths stood out as especially likely, and they were like clearly marked roads. But other less probable paths spun out in other directions, perceptible to his mind, but only barely, like dim trails through a strange forest.

He calmed himself further. He smoothed away the emotions of the outside world. He set aside his craving and desire. His mind emptied. And new things rushed in. The paths of the future exploded before him. What before was dim was now bright and easily perceived. His mind grew, comprehending the complexity before it.

The young man then made the first move. He chose a path that looked favorable to him. He glanced into it. On this path, he saw himself dash forward, block a strike from the old man, dodge to the left, and then sweep the old man's ankles.

Even as he perceived this possibility, it winked out of existence. The old man was master of the same power. He too was focusing his mind, peering into the many futures that could come to pass. By perceiving this particular possibility, the young man had brought it to the old man's attention. Then, once the old man knew of it, the possibility became impossible. The old man would not allow it to happen. Thus, it disappeared. What once could have been could no longer be.

The young man perceived several other strands of the future begin to grow in prominence, slowly turning from unlikely to likely. In one of them, the old man blocked a strike, then grabbed the hood of the young man's cloak, throwing him sharply to the ground, knocking him out. This was a path down which the old man would win. But now that the young man saw it, the path faded. Just as the old man had done, by perceiving this possibility, the young man countered it.

Lesser warriors would have been attacking each other, staffs twirling, robes flared in motion, pushing their skills to the limit. But in this contest, between these two men, there was no need for such things. Both of them could see into the future with extraordinary skill and precision. But nobody can see the future perfectly. The winner of this battle would be whoever could perceive the paths of the future further and more clearly than the other.

Standing perfectly still, the two of them battled ferociously, each trying to get a step ahead of the other.

Finally though, the paths of the future converged. The old master fought well, but his final move was blocked. A future that had been complex, swirling, and impenetrable became clear as day to the young man. It was a future where he won, and he saw clearly that the old man could not counter it. He exulted, triumphant.

The old master sagged, defeated. From his perspective, the future would have turned murky, impossible to see. He knew he had lost, but he could not perceive by what path. A look of sorrow came to his eyes. "So be it. I cannot stop you."

If the old master had been anyone else, the young man would have killed him at that moment. But against a master of his level, this was again unnecessary.

These two, able to see and feel the future, could bargain in ways that others cannot. When an ordinary man makes a promise, there is no way to tell for sure if he will keep it. He might keep his word, or he could choose to break it. But the young man could see the future more clearly than any other living person. And the old master knew that the young man could see the future clearly. So if the old man made a promise, the young man could see if the old man intended to keep it. And so the old man would only make a promise he intended to keep. In fact, the only way to offer such a promise was to be the sort of person who would never break it.

The old man spoke. "I will not interfere with your task tonight. And I will retreat from the world for a time. You will not hear from me for many years, if at all. But I will not retreat entirely. I will watch at the corners, waiting. I will not strike at you, of course. But I may interfere, on occasion. In small ways."

"Why should I accept this? I could kill you now where you stand, and there is nothing you can do about it. You have no leverage."

"That is incorrect. I have one bit of leverage left, and I intend to use it. You still care about me after all these years. You never intended to kill me, merely to defeat me. You did not prepare yourself to kill me tonight."

The old man was right, of course. The young man believed in what he was doing, and he was willing to kill. His hands were covered in blood already, and they would see more before this night was done. But he came here knowing his old master would choose life over death if it came to it. Unconsciously, the young man had counted on it. He wanted his old master to see how strong he had become, and he wanted the old man to live to remember it.

And so, the old man had some leverage after all. Not much. But enough to bargain with. Truthfully, it was a bold proposal. The young man nearly rejected it. But the old man had crafted it cleverly. There would be no other offer. If the young man did not take the deal, there would be no option left but to kill the old man. The offer was a carefully calculated risk.

"Dammit old man. Even when I win, you manage to get the better of me."

* * *

Some time later, the old man sat in the grass, crying. He could hear crickets chirping. Nearby, an owl hooted.

Then he heard the screams start to come from the monastery. He had done all he could for them. It hadn't been enough.

Gala 1

Gala woke up feeling cold and wet.

She forced her eyes open. She wasn't sure why she bothered; it was still dark out and she couldn't see a thing. But she could hear the rain pouring down outside her little pup tent. She reached out and felt a puddle to one side of her. Damn. The tent must have sprung a leak. She felt around in the dark, trying to find where the water was coming in. There it was. It was a small rip towards the top of the tent. Rain was dripping through in a thin, steady stream.

She felt around the top of her head and grabbed one of her packs. She was pretty sure she'd left the patch kit in this one. She opened it and began to rummage through, but she couldn't see anything. Changing tactics, she felt for one of the side pouches instead. She found her flashlight there, a big heavy thing. She'd seen two different movies where they used a flashlight just like it as a murder weapon. She hoped the batteries in it were still good. She pulled it out and flipped it on, but nothing happened. Dammit. She smacked the back of it in frustration. It suddeenly flashed to life, nearly blinding her with the brightness of it.

She took the flashlight in one hand and held it up a bit, angling it downward to shine where she was working. With her other hand, she shuffled through the pack again, now able to see what she was doing. After a few moments, she found what she was looking for. She took out a sheet of canvas with adhesive on it. The man who sold it to her said it was a special type of adhesive that would stick even when it was wet and raining. She was about to put that claim to the test. Using a pair of scissors she found in the pack as well, she began to cut away at the patch, shaping it roughly. It was harder than she expected because the scissors kept sticking to the adhesive. But she slowed down and finally got it cut down to a reasonable size.

Tucking the flashlight under one arm, she stepped outside of the tent. She was instantly soaked, but there wasn't much she could do about that. She saw that Maximian, her donkey, had made his way beneath a tree for a bit of shelter. He looked up at her with eyes that glinted in the harsh artificial light from her flashlight, tracking her movement and slowly swishing his tail.

Trying to shield the patch from the rain, she peeled the cover back off the adhesive, exposing the sticky part. She wiped away the droplets of water from the outside of the tent as best she could, then slapped the patch on. She didn't stick around to check to see how well it held, but hurried back into the tent, trying not to get any wetter than she already was.

It seemed like the patch was holding for now. The stream of water, at least, had stopped coming in. But her sleeping roll was soaked. She grabbed a rag out of her pack and used it to dry up what she could, or at least push the water around to the edge of the tent. Then, carefully maenuevering within the small tent, she stripped out of her wet clothing and put on something dry. Fortunately, her bags were made to be waterproof, so even though water had pooled around them, her clothing and gear were protected. She also pulled out her wristwatch and, using the flashlight, checked the time on its face. About 6:30am.

She figured there wasn't much point trying to get back to sleep. She flipped the flashlight off and stowed it back away, then just sat in the dark, alone with her thoughts.

She'd been having a strange dream right before the rain woke her up. She'd been back in the war, fighting through the jungle again. Except it wasn't the same jungle as last time. It was near a beach. She'd seen soldiers running through the surf, firing guns into the tree line. As she pictured it, she realized she knew the spot. It was a beach not far from Bell Harbor.

Her sleeping mind must have mixed everything all up. She hadn't come to Bell Harbor until after the war. After everything had gone all wrong. Bell Harbor was a peaceful little town, far away from anything important. This whole island was about as far away from anything important as she could find. That was the whole point of coming here, after all.

She continued to sit and brood for a while, until finally the sun started to come up. It was time for her to get going, regardless of the rain.

She stepped out of the tent and was treated to a gorgeous view. She had set up camp on top of a ridge looking down into a lush valley. The rising sun cut through the misty shroud of morning, casting shimmers of color that seemed to dance in front of her. She kept a small apartment back in Bell Harbor. But as often as not, she thought of this wilderness as her true home. Other people felt lonely out here. She did too, of course. But she felt lonely everywhere. She found it was often more painful to be lonely around other people than it was to be lonely by herself.

Her destination for the upcoming day was the top of a hill about five miles away. If it were clear, she'd have been able to see it from where she stood, but right now the rain and fog obscured it. She knew where it was though and she knew how to get there. Given the terrain, it would be about a five hour hike, maybe longer if the rain kept going. Her course would skirt around the valley, sticking to the highlands. The hills were tough terrain, but hacking through the lowland jungle would be even tougher. It was dangerously easy to get lost down there. Up here in the highlands, the vegetation was thinner, mostly small trees and grasses. Sometimes she had no choice but to cut through the lowlands, but she stuck to the hills when she could manage it.

She quickly broke camp, loading her gear on Maximian's back. The docile creature stood still, accustomed to the routine. She patted him on his head and fed him a sugar cube. She untied his line from a nearby tree and led him out on to the path she had chosen for the day.

After a few hours, the rain finally stopped. She took out her bed roll and wet clothes, laying them out flat across Maximian's back. She hoped the midday sun would dry them out a bit.

It quickly warmed up after that, and the mist cleared. Gala started to sweat a bit from the warmth. Weather often changed quickly out here. She could see her destination now though, a tall hill that rose from the forest, still a couple miles away.

The final climb up the hill was challenging, but she and Maximian were used to it. She was only just starting to become winded when she reached the top. She gave herself a few minutes to rest, but her work for the day wasn't done yet. The next part was why she had come all this way.

She pulled several larger bags off Maximian's back and revealed a number of complex metal devices. She began to assmble them at the very top part of the hill. Her reason for coming here was to survey the surrounding land. Her equipment was specialized for the task, allowing her to precisely measure the angles between herself and any point she could see. By collecting measurements from several different hills, she could triangulate the precise location of various landmarks. Done properly, she could use the data she collected to produce high quality topographical maps.

It was difficult work, but it paid well. Many people here on the island had a use for accurate maps. More importantly, it gave her a great deal of freedom to operate on her own, alone out here in the wilderness. In more civilized lands, this sort of work would be done by large, well-equipped surveying teams. But here on this island, it was just her and Maximian.

She was comfortable working alone, but she did wish sometimes she had someone to return home to. Every time she got back to Bell Harbor, her apartment felt cold, empty, lifeless. She'd had someone once, many years ago, but she'd thrown all that away. Foolishly.

She worked for several more hours, collecting measurements, recording everything carefully in her notebook. She worked quickly but precisely, double-checking each figure. If one or two points were off, she could probably fix things once she got back. But too many mistakes would ruin the whole expedition.

The sun creeping near the horizon was her signal to wrap things up. She needed to set up camp while she still had some daylight left. As she was putting her equipment away though, she noticed something unexpected.

She saw a plane emerge from some clouds above her head, trailing smoke behind it. It was a newer style of plane with just one pair of wings and a propeller out in front of the nose. That stuck out to her. Most of the planes she'd seen out here were the older style, with two sets of wings stacked on top of each other.

Then she realized what else was strange. She couldn't hear it. Usually a plane flying out here in the wilderness was noisy, audible for miles around. Maybe this type was quieter than she was used to?

She saw that the plane was angled down, getting closer to the ground each moment. And then she noticed that the propeller wasn't spinning. That's why the plane was silent. The engine was dead. Was that related to the smoke she saw trailing behind it? She watched in horror as the plane continued down, headed towards the dense jungle below.

Gala moved fast. She pulled her survey equipment back out with shaky hands. She watched and waited, poised, until finally the plane crashed into the treetops. Trying to stay calm, she counted out nine seconds between when she saw the plane hit and when she heard the crash. That meant it was about two miles away. Carefully, she used her instruments to spot where the plane fell and read off the measurements. Her hands still shaking slightly, she did some quick math. She sketched out the area she'd just finished mapping and placed the crash site on the map. She looked back again to double-check. Her map looked good.

As she finished that, she heard engines. She looked up, surprised, and saw two more planes of a similar design coming in from the same direction as the first plane. Good. They must have seen the first plane go down. Maybe they could help.

She watched for a few minutes as they passed overhead. Then she saw the two planes dip down, angled towards the site of the crash. What were they doing? Were they trying to get a look?

To her horror, she heard the sound of guns firing. Squinting, she could see tracer rounds ripping through the air. The two planes swooped over the crash site, raking it with gunfire. Then the two planes pulled up and flew away.

She thought furiously on what it could mean. Whoever was on that plane, the others must really want them dead. But with all the foliage... there's no way they could know if the job was done. They'd need to come back on foot to finish the job. And the nearest airstrip was back in Bell Harbor, two days away at least. With all the hills out here, there was no way they'd try and land anywhere closer.

She snapped her notebook shut and closed her eyes. What was she doing? This wasn't any of her business. She thought back to last time she let herself get caught up in things that weren't her problem. It hadn't gone well.

But she flipped the notebook back open anyway, seeing the map she just finished sketching. She couldn't help but start planning her route. She could get down there in about three hours, she figured. She'd have to do the last of it in the dark, which would be difficult. But she knew she could manage it.

Dammit. She couldn't just leave someone down there to die. Maybe she was a fool. No, she absolutely was a fool. She knew that for certain. But if she was going to be a fool, maybe she could be a useful fool.